Hello, this is Dr. Dong
-Zan. In this lecture, we'll
discuss a few lipid
metabolism related disorders.
Here's the learning
objectives to help you how
to learn this particular
lecture. But overall,
we'll try to apply what
you have learned in
the cholesterol
biosynthesis lecture and the
lipoprotein lecture.
and to explain some of
the clinical manifestation
of these disorders,
and also try to better
understand why certain
drugs that can be used
to treat these disorders.
And this table nicely
summarized the disorders
related to
lipoproteins, right? And
there's two big family
of them. One is called
Hypo, right? Hypo means
lower than normal.
Hypo lipoproteinemia, right?
And conversely,
they're also hyper,
right? Hyper means
higher than normal levels.
So hyper lipoproteinemia.
And we'll discuss
them one by one.
So, here I present you a
general strategy in terms
of how you identify and
treat clinical conditions.
And obviously, these are
simplified strategies,
and in reality, it's going
to be more complicated.
But anyway, so if you
could, first identify
which gene in the patient
is mutated. Right.
And then you need to think
about what is the normal
physiological function
of the protein that
encoded by the mutated
genes. Right. And from there,
and you can try to see
if you could rationalize
the clinical manifestation
and based on the
physiological function
that you already know. And
hopefully you'll find
actionable pharmacological
intervention that to
compensate or crack the defect.
So first we want to discuss the
hyperlipoproteinemia, right?
Again, hyper indicating
that these individuals
has higher level
of lipoprotein than
a healthy individual.
So the first, the type
1 hyperlipoproteinemia
is also called familial
lipoprotein lipase
deficiency, right?
Just from the name that
indicating the lipase
LPL is deficient, right?
And this could due to
either the genes that
encoding the LPL is mutated,
right? As you recall,
we discussed that the
function of the LPL is
to digest or transfer
the triglycerides from
carlomicron into peripheral
tissues. In addition,
for the VLDL, they also
digest the triglycerides
in the VLDL and transfer
these free fatty
acids or lipids into
the peripheral tissues.
In addition, if you
recall, we also discussed
that one of the apoprotein
called APOC2, and APOC2
can be found both on the
carbon micron as well
as the VLDL, right? The
major function of APOLC2
is to activate the
enzyme activities of LPL.
So as you can imagine,
that mutation that
happened in the gene
that encoding APOLC2
leads to the not sufficient
activation of the LPL.
Right. So because the
critical function of LPL
in digesting the
triglycerides from chalomicron
from VLDL. Right. So
therefore, that would lead to
the increased chalomicron
and VLDL in the blood.
Right. And as you recall,
the LDL is a metabolized
VLDL. right? Because
the VLDL increase,
its metabolite LDL
obviously going to decrease,
right? And we also discussed
that when HDL is first
synthesized, they are also
called nascent HDL, right?
Nascent HDL has a lot of
apoproteins, but don't
have a whole lot of
lipid triglycerides and
cholesterol and during the
maturation process from
the nascent hdl to the
mature hdl it pick up many
lipid from the color
micron or from the vldl at
the same time transfer
some of the april protein
to the nascent chylomicron
and nascent ldl
right therefore when
you have increased
chylomicron vldl
affecting the maturation
of the hdl right
therefore the hdl level in
the patient is also
reduced but interestingly
these individuals
actually don't have any
increased risk for
coronary disease.
So that type 2
hyperlipropotinemia is
also called familial
hypercholesterolemia,
right? Again, as
the name indicated,
the patient is going
to have higher levels
of cholesterol in
their blood, Right.
And as you recall,
during the uptake
of LDL by either the
peripheral cells or mainly
by the liver. Right.
And the LDL is recognized by
liver through the
LDL receptors.
Right. The same thing.
Similarly, you can find LDL
receptor in the peripheral
cells also. But when you
have genetic mutations in
the LDL receptors, obviously
the hepatocyte could not
uptake the LDL efficiently.
That leads to the increase
of LDL level in the blood.
In addition, we'll also
mention that one of the
apoproteins on the LDL
-ApoB100 function as
the recognition signal
for the LDL receptors,
right? So obviously when
you have genetic mutations
in the ApoB100, it
could not get recognized
by the LDL receptor
more efficiently, right?
And that also
affecting the uptake
of LDL particles
by the hepatocytes.
And in addition, there's
a third protein called
PCSK9. And in the next
slides, we'll discuss how
PCSK9 affecting the turnover
of the LDL receptor.
So either way, mutations
that are affecting these
three proteins will lead
to the increased level of
LDL in the blood. And
because LDL is the major
carrier of cholesterols in
the blood, and that leads
to the increased level of
cholesterol in the blood
also. and obviously this
could lead to higher risk
of the individual to develop
the coronary disease.
The PCSK9 is a serum
protease, right?
So its major function is
when PCSK9 gets secreted
outside the cells, it can
bind to the LDL receptor and
and targeted for lysosomal
degradation right so
therefore the function of
pcsk9 is to reduce the cell
surface level of ldl receptor
right again ldl receptor
promote uptake of ldl
particle by the hepatocytes
so if you could inhibit
the pcsk9 and you're going
to increase the cell
surface level of the ldl
receptors and that could
accelerate the uptake of the
fdl particles and that
could reduce the cholesterol
level in in the blood and
currently there's two uh
pcs k9 inhibitors has been
approved about uh fda uh
one is uh a little a little
combo and ebola come up
right so these two drugs
are actually monoclonal
antibodies right they bind
to the pcsk9 and preventing
its function in terms of
accelerating the
ldr ldr receptors
so the uh the type uh
three uh familiar uh
hyperlipopenemia is
due to the mutations
in the genes that
including APOE, right,
and as you recall that
during the maturation process
of chylomicrons and VLDL,
and they pick up APOE
from the HDL, right, and
one of the functions of
APOE is a bind to the
receptors on the hepalocytes
or peripheral tissues and
facilitating the uptake
of color micron remnant
and VLDL remnants, right?
So therefore, if you block
the downstream uptake,
and that leads to the
increased level of color
microns and VLDLs in the
blood. And these patients
also have increased risk
of coronary disease.
And the type 4
hyperlipoproteinemia is also
called familiar
hypertriacylglycerol, right? Again,
from the name that
indicated these individuals
often have higher level
of triacylglycerols
in their blood right and
usually when uh you have
too much glucose uh or
in in in your diet or in
the blood or glucose cannot
be metabolized uh through
other pathways uh it get
converted into acetyl
-CoA, right? These acetyl
-CoA from glucose then be
utilized to synthesize
free fatty acid. Free fatty
acid then assembled become
triacylglycerols and
then they got packaged
into the VLDL, right? So
therefore, when you have
excess level of glucose,
that leads to the
overproduction of the VLDL,
right? And And therefore,
that leads to the increased
level of valdeal in the
blood. And also when
you monitor the triacylglycerols
or triglycerides,
its level is also increased.
And these individuals
usually associate
with high risk of
coronary heart disease,
type 2 diabetes,
as well as obesity.
All right. So now we're
going to switch gear and
discuss a few
hypolipoproteinemia, right? Again,
hypol usually means
lower than normal level.
And this table summarizes
the few hypolipoproteinemia,
and we're going to
discuss them one by one.
So, the first one is called
Tangier disease, right?
For the Tangier disease, it
has a mutation in the genes
encoding ABCA1, right?
If you recall, the major
physiological function for
ABCA1 is to flip the cholesterol
from the inner leaflet
of membrane to the outer
leaflet of the membrane right
so that HDL can pick up the
cholesterol level and become
the mature HDL and also
transport these cholesterols
back to the liver right
so when you have defect
in in terms of flipping
these cholesterols, right?
Therefore, it reduced the
ability of HDL to pick up
these cholesterols, right?
Therefore, it's affecting
its maturation process.
And what you see
in this patient
is reduced the level of HDL.
So the second
hypolipoproteinemia
is called A-beta
lipoproteinemia, right? A,
indicating abnormal,
beta is referring to this
particular apoprotein,
apoprotein proteins, right?
So, as you recall, that
apoprotein are critical
for the assembly of color
microns and VLDL. For
the color microns, it
requires the apoprotein 48.
For the VLDL, it requires
the apoprotein 100, right?
And in addition, both of them
require another protein, MTP,
which help to load the
lipids on either APOB48
or APOB100, right? But
for individuals that had
mutations in the gene
that encoding the MTP,
that's going to lead
to the package of color
microns and VLDL defective,
right? So the result
is the calomicron levels
and the VLDL levels in
the patient's blood is
going to be lower, right?
And because IDL and LDL,
they're metabolites of
VLDL, and their level is
not surprisingly lower also.
So the third
hypolipoproteinemia called also
called hypoalpha
lipoproteinemia, right? This
alpha refers to the
apoprotein A containing
lipoprotein, right? If
you recall that apoprotein
is a critical component
for the HDL, right? So,
HDL is often synthesized in
the liver and intestines.
When HDL is first
synthesized, it's also called
nascent HDL, right? Because
it has a lot of protein,
apoprotein, has less lipid,
it shows in a disc shape,
right? And HDL transfer ApoE
and ApoC2 to both pyromicron
and VLDL and help their
maturations. And ApoA1,
so one of the Apo proteins
help to activate the
enzyme lcat right as you
recall lcat add a cell group
to the free cholesterols and
generating the cholesterol
easter right to help to
keep the cholesterols
inside the hdl right that was
also part of the maturation
process also right so
therefore when you have a
defect in one of these ApoA
proteins, you're going to
have a defect in the
maturation of the HDL, right?
So therefore,
these individuals' manifest
have a lower level of HDL.
And next, we're going to
discuss a few more genetic
diseases related to the
lipoprotein, right? The first one
is called Wolman disease.
And for the Wolman disease
patient, And this is there
due to the deficiency of
one of the lysosomal acid
lipase, right? As you recall,
lysosome is the major kind of
recycling all the materials.
And when the lipoprotein
particles get taken into the
cells, it fuses with the
lysosome and the other
enzymes within the lysosome,
including the lipase that
help to degrade the contents
in these particles right
to recycle them so obviously
when you have defect in
some of these lipase
right the lysosome then
cannot efficiently degrade
these different lipids
leads to abnormal accumulation
of either cholesterol
or triglycerides in
the cells cells and
therefore affecting
different cellular functions.
Another disease related
to the lipoprotein is the
mutation that happened in
these genes we just mentioned,
LCET.
Again, LCET adds an acyl
group to the cholesterol,
converting them to
cholesterol esters. So,
because the critical role
of LCET in the maturation
of the HDL when the enzyme
is deficient and the
individuals manifest lower
HDL levels, and because
HDL function as reverse
cholesterol transporter,
in this patient you
also observe accumulated
cholesterol levels
in the periphery.
tissues. And for the
fatty liver, right, this
is often due to neither
the liver doesn't
have enough energy that
can be used to synthesize
proteins or missing
some of the amino acid
or compromises ability
to synthesize choline,
which is a critical
precursor for phosphatidyl
choline, which is a
phospholipid. Again,
the phospholipid is critical
for the package
of lipoproteins.
And therefore, in this,
when you have compromised
ability to synthesize
VLDL and the triglyceride
synthesizer in the liver,
kind of stuck in the
liver, right, that leads
to the disease called fatty
liver so when you have
abnormal level of different
lipoproteins it's going
to cause increased risk
of cardiovascular disease
right and as we discussed
previously HDL function
to reverse transport
the cholesterol from the
peripheral tissues back
to the livers right in
addition and also help to
reduce the oxidized
ldl as we discuss in
the next few slides
that the oxidized ldl
can cause damage
to the blood vessel
and LDL one of the the
reason that high level of LDL
is not good is because the
LDL can be easily damaged
by a variety of free
radicals right and damaged
LDL can be engulfed by
the microphages which then
become the so-called foam cells.
Foam cells then accumulate
in different blood vessels
and eventually leads
to the clotting of these
different blood vessels.
All right. So,
you know, because
the atherosclerosis
related to the lipoprotein,
so we're going to
briefly discuss this.
I'm sure you'll learn
more about this in
other lectures also.
So here's the cross-section
view of the different
blood vessels, right?
So you have endotheta
cells in the cavity of the
blood vessels, and then
you have muscles surrounding
the endotheta cells
that help the contraction
of the blood vessel.
So as I mentioned, you know,
one of the problems with
the LDL or higher level
of LDL, they are because
they are easily get damaged
by a variety of free
radicals I mean there can
be a quite a lot inside the
bodies right and to counter
that you know there's also
a variety of antioxidants
like vitamin e vitamin c
and beta carotene right but
when the free radical and
the antioxidant are
imbalanced and that leads to
the accumulation of the uh
the damaged or oxidized ldl
right so oxidized ldl is
not good right so uh the
they are recognized by the
macrophages uh as kind of
you know toxic molecules
right therefore the
macrophages uh engulf these
uh damaged ldl and eventually
form these so-called
foam cells right and
accumulation of these foam
cells leads to the plaque
formation in various blood
vessels and the plaque
too much of it leads to
the fission right and
then they certainly can be
some of them can be healed
but then they cause
rupture again Then these
cycles eventually leads to
the clogging of the blood
vessel and manifests as
atherosclerosis plaque.
So how to better control
the serine cholesterol
levels? And probably
easier way is by
changing one's lifestyle
or mainly the diets.
right for example you know
obviously if you reduce
the the lipids and the
cholesterols in your diet
and that help to reduce the
whole cholesterol levels
in the blood and in the
cholesterol biosynthesis lecture
we also discussed that
plants usually don't have a
whole lot of cholesterols but
they do contain cholesterol
-like molecules right
including stenos and steroids
right both stenos and
steroids and they don't get
absorbed as efficiently as
the cholesterol by the small
intestines right so on the
other hand the stenos and the
steroids actually can help
to lower the absorbs the
rate of cholesterol in the
diet right so therefore when
you eat a lot of vegetables
or plant-based diets that's
going to help you lower
the cholesterol level or
ball right and also the fiber
in the in the diet can also
reduce the cholesterol
uptake right and the weight
reduction and exercise can
increase your hdr levels can
help therefore help you
lower the cholesterol levels
And, you know, you can
certainly use drugs to
control the cholesterol
levels, right? Again, as we
discussed in the cholesterol
biosynthesis level,
the enzyme HMG-CoA reductase
catalyze the re-limiting
step of the biosynthesis
inside our body, right?
Obviously, if you block
the activities of HMG-CoA
reductase, and you're going
to reduce the endosinate
-synthetized cholesterol levels,
right? So that's what these
family drugs, statin,
their mechanism of actions.
And in this lecture,
we'll discuss
the function of PCSK9, right?
PCSK9 basically accelerates
the degradation of LDL
receptors, right? if you
can inhibit pcsk9 and you're
going to slow down the
turnover of the ldl receptors
the ldl receptor uh get a
chance to re uptake more
ldl particles and also in
the uh cholesterol lecture
we discuss that cholesterol
is the precursor to
synthesize about acid right
and bias is some of it,
you know, can be cycled
outside the body. And if you
could block the reabsorption
of bioacid, right, so
that could indirectly reduce
the cholesterol levels.
And we also mentioned
that one of the vitamins,
vitamin B3, or niacin, for
whatever reason, it can
also reduce the the LDL
levels, right? And we also
mentioned that niacin can
reduce a kind of a harmful
lipoprotein, LPA, and
increase the level of LPA
correlating with the high
risk of coronary disease.
The drug fibrate can
inhibit the hepatic release
of lipoprotein, which
reduce the blood level of
VLDL reduce their
triglycerides and in addition
of hybrid can potentially
the action of the LPL
right again help to
facilitate the digestion
of the lipid inside VLDL
and color microns right
and fiber it can also
increase the HDL levels right
and you can certainly
combine some of this drug
together. That's the drug
Zetia. It's basically combined
the drugs to inhibit the
dietary absorption of
cholesterol and at the same
time, using a statin to
inhibit the endosinally
synthesized cholesterols.
This table lists all
the drugs that we just
talking about and finally
there's this family
disease that collectively
called metabolic
syndrome right they also
call syndrome x or insulin
resistance syndrome
and and these patients
manifest a variety of
metabolic abnormalities right
which increase their risk
of cardiovascular disease
as well as diabetes and
these individuals usually
have a larger waist race
and their triglycerol
level in the blood usually
pretty high and their
good cholesterol HDL level
usually lower than normal
with that this is the last
slides again this is the
summary slides and try to
use the slides to guide
you study this lectures
okay thank you very much